<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<species-list>
    <species>
        <latin>Abies grandis</latin>
        <common>Grand Fir</common>
        <description>This is the finest and commonest of the firs but is rare in Bristol. A fir native to the Pacific Northwest and Northern California of North America, occurring at altitudes of sea level to 1,800 m. It is a major constituent of the Grand Fir/Douglas Fir Eco region of the Cascade Range.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer</latin>
        <common>Maple</common>
        <description>A genus of trees or shrubs commonly known as maple. There are approximately 128
            species, most of which are native to Asia,with a number also appearing in Europe,
            northern Africa, and North America. Only one species,Acer laurinum, extends to the
            Southern Hemisphere.The type species of the genus is the sycamore maple,Acer
            pseudoplatanus, the most common maple species in Europe.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer negundo</latin>
        <common>Box Elder Maple</common>
        <altname>Ash Leaf Maple</altname>
        <altname>Maple Ash</altname>
        <description>A species of maple native to North America. Box elder, boxelder maple,
            ash-leaved maple, and maple ash are its most common names in the United States; in
            Britain and Ireland it is also known as ash leaf maple as its leaves are quite unlike
            other maples, it has attractive flowers in spring, and pretty shoots when young, but it
            does not Age well. Commonly planted.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer opalus</latin>
        <common>Italian Maple</common>
        <description>A rare tree looking almost identical to a Sycamore, but with blunter leaves,
            that flowers at the end of February. It is native to the hills and mountains of southern
            and western Europe, from Italy to Spain and north to southern Germany, and also in
            northwest Africa in Morocco and Algeria.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer palmatum</latin>
        <common>Japanese Maple</common>
        <altname>Smooth Japanese Maple</altname>
        <description>A species of woody plant native to Japan, China, Korea, eastern Mongolia, and
            southeast Russia. A slow growing small tree with amazing autumn colour, that is widely
            planted in gardens, but rarely in parks.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer platanoides</latin>
        <common>Norway Maple</common>
        <description>A species of maple native to eastern and central Europe and western Asia, from
            France east to Russia, north to southern Scandinavia and southeast to northern Iran. It
            is a member of the soapberry and lychee family. Very commonly planted in recent years,
            with a wide variety of leaf colours, this species grows very fast, and is distinguished
            from the Sycamore by pointed tips to its leaves, and a bark that is vertically
            striated.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer platanoides 'Crimson King'</latin>
        <common>Norway Maple 'Crimson King'</common>
        <description>Acer can be deciduous trees or large shrubs with paired, often palmately-lobed leaves and small flowers followed by characteristic winged fruits. 'Crimson King' is a vigorous medium-sized deciduous tree. Leaves large, 5-lobed, deep purplish-crimson all summer. Flowers reddish-orange, in clusters on leafless branches.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer pseudoplatanus</latin>
        <common>Sycamore</common>
        <description>Known as the sycamore in the United Kingdom and the sycamore maple in the
            United States, is a flowering plant species in the soapberry and lychee family
            Sapindaceae. It is one of the commonest trees in the city, almost all self-sown, though
            variegated forms are planted and a rare form with a purple underside to the leaf is
            occasional.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer pseudoplatanus f. variegatum</latin>
        <common>Variegated Sycamore Maple</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer rubrum</latin>
        <common>Red Maple</common>
        <description>One of the most common and widespread deciduous trees of eastern and central
            North America. The U.S. Forest service recognizes it as the most commonplace native tree
            in eastern North America. Distinguished by flowers in March and early start to red
            autumn colour in September.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer saccharinum</latin>
        <common>Silver Maple</common>
        <description>A fast growing Maple with pretty leaves that have a pale underside turning
            silver in the Autumn. It flowers in January and its seeds fall at the end of May. Widely
            planted in recent years.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Aesculus flava</latin>
        <common>Yellow Buckeye Chestnut</common>
        <altname>Common Buckeye</altname>
        <altname>Sweet Buckeye</altname>
        <description>A species of deciduous tree. It is native to the Ohio Valley and Appalachian
            Mountains of the Eastern United States.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Aesculus hippocastanum</latin>
        <common>Horse Chestnut</common>
        <description>The tree is not native to this country. It originates from Greece. Some have
            growths and swellings on their trunks and branches. They are almost certainly caused by
            a bacterium, Agrobacterium tumefaciens which infects the tree to produce these crown
            galls. The bacteria live naturally in the soil and gain access to the tree through a
            wound, often at soil surface level. The bacteria congregate in large colonies causing
            these substantial growths. Although the galls look as if they could be seriously
            affecting the health of the tree, they do no real damage as the bacteria are dependent
            on the host tree remaining healthy in order to complete their development. Agrobacterium
            tumefaciens is known to use more than 600 other plant species, on all of which it will
            produce some form of crown gall.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Aesculus turbinata</latin>
        <common>Japanese Chestnut</common>
        <altname>Japanese Horse-chestnut</altname>
        <description>A rare tree with large leaves with seven leaflets on each. It is native to
            Japan but cultivated elsewhere. It is a tree up to 30 m tall. Flowers are white to pale
            yellowish with red spots. Capsules are dark brown, obovoid to pyriform.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Aesculus x carnea</latin>
        <common>Red Horse Chestnut</common>
        <altname>Red Chestnut</altname>
        <parent>Aesculus pavia</parent>
        <parent>Aesculus hippocastanum</parent>
        <description>An artificial hybrid between A. pavia and A. hippocastanum. The origin of the tree is not known, but it probably first appeared in Germany before 1820.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ailanthus altissima</latin>
        <common>Tree of Heaven</common>
        <description>Commonly known as tree of heaven, ailanthus, or in Standard Chinese as
            chouchun, is a deciduous tree in the Simaroubaceae family. It is native to both
            northeast and central China, as well as Taiwan, often planted, that suckers very readily
            and flowers in late July, and has crimson winged fruit. Otherwise it can be mistaken for
            an ash.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Alnus cordata</latin>
        <common>Italian Alder</common>
        <description>A tree or shrub species belonging to the family of Betulaceae and native to
            southern Apennine Mountains and north-eastern mountains of Corsica, it has been recently
            planted in parks and as a street tree. It is fast growing and almost
            evergreen.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Alnus glutinosa</latin>
        <common>Common Alder</common>
        <altname>Black Alder</altname>
        <altname>European Alder</altname>
        <altname>Alder</altname>
        <description>A species of tree in the family Betulaceae, native to most of Europe, southwest
            Asia and northern Africa. It is common on stream-ways, and some have suffered from a
            disease in recent years. Occasionally planted on drier sites.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Alnus glutinosa 'Laciniata'</latin>
        <common>Cut Leaved Alder</common>
        <description>This is an attractive slow growing variety of the Common Alder.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Alnus incana</latin>
        <common>Grey Alder</common>
        <description>A species of alder with a wide range across the cooler parts of the Northern
            Hemisphere, it is Uncommon in Bristol.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Amelanchier x grandiflora 'Robin Hill'</latin>
        <description>Amelanchier are small deciduous trees or shrubs with showy white flowers in early spring, red to purple fruits and often good autumn colour. 'Robin Hill' forms a dense, upright small tree, spreading with age. The pale pink flowers open from pink buds then fade to white, and are followed by dark purple berries. The foliage opens bronzy, turns green in summer and produces orange and red shades in autumn.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Araucaria araucana</latin>
        <common>Monkey Puzzle Tree</common>
        <description>An evergreen tree growing to 1-1.5 m in diameter and 30-40 m in height. It is
            native to central and southern Chile and western Argentina. Araucaria araucana is the
            hardiest species in the conifer genus Araucaria. It is quite often planted in private
            gardens.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Arbutus unedo</latin>
        <common>Strawberry Tree</common>
        <description>An evergreen shrub or small tree in the family Ericaceae, native to the
            Mediterranean region and western Europe north to western France and Ireland. It fruits
            and flowers in November.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Azara microphylla</latin>
        <common>Box-leaf Azara</common>
        <description>Delightful, evergreen shrubs or small trees with simple leaves, often in
            unequal pairs, and very small, fragrant yellow flowers with prominent stamens in
            clusters or spikes from the leaf axils, occasionally followed by white or pale purple
            berries</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Betula albosinensis</latin>
        <common>Birch</common>
        <description>A species of birch in the family Betulaceae, native to Western China. It is a
            deciduous tree growing to 25 metres. A particular feature is the peeling brown
            bark.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Betula ermanii</latin>
        <common>Erman's Birch</common>
        <description>A rugged species of birch tree belonging to the family Betulaceae. It is an
            extremely variable species and can be found in Northeast China, Korea, Japan, and
            Russian Far East. It can grow to 20 metres tall.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Betula pendula</latin>
        <common>Silver Birch</common>
        <altname>Warty Birch</altname>
        <description>A species of tree in the family Betulaceae, native to Europe and parts of Asia,
            though in southern Europe it is only found at higher altitudes. A very common pioneer
            tree, also widely planted. It rarely lives long, and can't survive shade.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Betula utilis</latin>
        <common>Himalayan Birch</common>
        <description>Native to the Himalayas, growing at elevations up to 4,500 m. The specific
            epithet, utilis, refers to the many uses of the different parts of the tree. This is now
            a very common species grown for its fine white bark which is sometimes damaged by people
            pulling it off in strips.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Betula utilis var jacquemontii</latin>
        <common>West Himalayan Birch</common>
        <altname>Jaquemont's Birch</altname>
        <description>It is named after the French botanist, Victor Jaquemont who worked in India. The tree occurs in the wild from Kashmir eastwards to Nepal, but crosses with the Himalayan Birch (Betula edulis) to produce intermeriate forms, where the bark becomes progressively less white as you move eastwards. The bark of Himalayan Birch was used centuries ago in India as paper for writing lengthy scriptures and texts in Sanskrit and other scripts, particularly in historical Kashmir. Its use as paper for books is mentioned by early Sanskrit writers. The bark is still used for writing sacred mantras, which are placed in an amulet and worn around the neck for protection or blessing. The bark is widely used for packaging material (particularly butter), roof construction, umbrella covers, bandages, and more. The wood is also used for bridge construction, and the foliage for fodder. Its most widespread use is for firewood, which has caused large areas of habitat to be eliminated or reduced.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Calocedrus decurrens</latin>
        <common>Incense Cedar</common>
        <altname>California Incense-cedar</altname>
        <description>A species of conifer native to western North America, with the bulk of the
            range in the United States, from central western Oregon through most of California and
            the extreme west of Nevada, and also a short distance into northwest Mexico in northern
            Baja California. It grows at altitudes of 50?2900 m. It is the most widely known species
            in the genus, and is often simply called 'incense cedar' without the regional
            qualifier.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Carpinus betulus</latin>
        <common>HornBeam</common>
        <description>A hornbeam native to Western Asia and central, eastern, and southern Europe,
            including southern England. It is a native tree, in appearance similar to a
            Beech.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Carpinus betulus 'Fastigiata'</latin>
        <common>European Hornbeam</common>
        <description>A hornbeam native to Western Asia and central, eastern, and southern Europe,
            including southern England.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Carpinus betulus 'Frans Fontaine'</latin>
        <common>Common Hornbeam 'Frans Fontaine'</common>
        <description>Grows to a height of approximately 10 meters, but only 3 meters wide. Unlike
            the more ubiquitous 'Fastigiata' form, Frans Fontaine preserves the attractive lateral
            boughs of the species and retains its columnar habit throughout its life. Slow to
            moderate growth rate.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Castanea sativa</latin>
        <common>Sweet Chestnut</common>
        <description>A species of flowering plant in the family Fagaceae, native to Europe and Asia
            Minor, and widely cultivated throughout the temperate world.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Catalpa bignonioides</latin>
        <common>Indian Bean Tree</common>
        <description>A species of Catalpa that is native to the southeastern United States in
            Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, and Mississippi. Common names include southern
            catalpa, cigartree, and Indian-bean-tree. An attractive tree with large floppy leaves,
            fairly fast growth and white flowers in July that give rise to long thin beans. In
            recent years newly planted ones have tended to develop splits in their
            branches.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cedrus atlantica</latin>
        <common>Atlas Cedar</common>
        <description>This comes from the Atlas Mountains of North Africa, and a very striking blue
            form is often grown. Its branches grow upwards, unlike the other two
            cedars.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cedrus atlantica 'Glauca'</latin>
        <common>Blue Atlas Cedar</common>
        <description>Originates from the Atlas mountains in Algeria and Morocco. This blue form is the most common variety planted in many parks in Britain. It is a fast growing tree, the girth can reach 2.5 metres in just 50 years. It can reach a height of 40 metres in this country.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cedrus deodara</latin>
        <common>Deodar Cedar</common>
        <altname>Deodar</altname>
        <description>A species of cedar native to the western Himalayas in eastern Afghanistan,
            northern Pakistan and India, southwesternmost Tibet in and western Nepal, occurring at
            1,500-3,200 m altitude.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cedrus libani</latin>
        <common>Cedar of Lebanon</common>
        <description>An evergreen coniferous tree growing up to 40m (130ft) tall, with a trunk up to
            2.5 m (8 ft 2 in) in diameter. The crown is conic when young, becoming broadly tabular
            with age with fairly level branches.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Celtis occidentalis</latin>
        <common>Hackberry</common>
        <altname>Common Hackberry</altname>
        <description>This is a rare tree. It is a large deciduous tree native to North America. It
            is also known as the nettletree, sugarberry, beaverwood, northern hackberry, and
            American hackberry.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cercidiphyllum japonicum</latin>
        <common>Katsura</common>
        <description>Originating from China and introduced into the UK in 1881. In Asia it is one of
            the largest deciduous trees, growing to 10 - 45 metres tall. It is a very primitive
            hardwood species, closely related to the Magnolias and is unusual in having some
            features of a conifer or softwood. Each tree is a separate male or female. The family is
            a very primitive one and may even predate the Ginkgo. In autumn, when the leaves change
            colour to a beautiful pale yellow, pinks and reds, they give off a smell of burnt sugar
            or caramel. Generally, they are smelled before they are seen during this short two-week
            period. When fully grown this is a fine tree that grows its leaves all down its
            branches.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Chamaecyparis lawsoniana</latin>
        <common>Lawson's cypress cultivar</common>
        <altname>Port Orford Cedar</altname>
        <parent>Cupressus macrocarpa</parent>
        <parent>Cupressus nootkatensis</parent>
        <description>Known as Port Orford cedar or Lawson cypress, is a species of conifer in the genus Chamaecyparis, family Cupressaceae. This is the most commonly planted Cypress, in parks gardens and cemeteries everywhere, with a wide variety of forms. They sometimes grow with multiple trunks from close to the ground.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Chamaecyparis lawsoniana 'Lutea'</latin>
        <common>Lawson's cypress 'Lutea'</common>
        <description>Chamaecyparis are evergreen trees, usually of narrowly ovoid or columnar outline, with much-branched sprays of small scale-like leaves, and small, globose cones; tiny red male cones are conspicuous in a few cultivars. 'Lutea' is a broadly columnar evergreen conifer making a medium-sized tree with drooping sprays of golden-yellow foliage.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Chamaecyparis lawsoniana 'Erecta Viridis'</latin>
        <common>Lawson's cypress 'Erecta Viridis'</common>
        <description>Chamaecyparis are evergreen trees, usually of narrowly ovoid or columnar
            outline, with much-branched sprays of small scale-like leaves, and small, globose cones;
            tiny red male cones are conspicuous in a few cultivars. 'Erecta Viridis' is a columnar
            tree to 20m, with erect branches bearing flat, upright sprays of rich green
            foliage.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Chamaecyparis lawsoniana 'Fraseri'</latin>
        <common>Lawson's cypress 'Fraseri'</common>
        <description>Chamaecyparis are evergreen trees, usually of narrowly ovoid or columnar
            outline, with much-branched sprays of small scale-like leaves, and small, globose cones;
            tiny red male cones are conspicuous in a few cultivars.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cupressus nootkatensis</latin>
        <synomym>Chamaecyparis nootkatensis</synomym>
        <common>Nootka cypress</common>
        <description>A species of trees in the cypress family native to the coastal regions of northwestern North America.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Chamaecyparis obtusa</latin>
        <common>Hinoki Cypress</common>
        <description>A species of cypress native to central Japan. It is a slow-growing tree which
            grows to 35 m tall with a trunk up to 1 m in diameter. The bark is dark
            red-brown.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Chamaecyparis pisifera 'Filifera Aurea'</latin>
        <common>Sawara Cypress 'Filifera Aurea'</common>
        <description>A species of false cypress, native to central and southern Japan, on the
            islands of Honshu and Kyushu. 'Filifera Aurea' is a slow-growing evergreen conifer making
            a large broadly conical shrub of open habit, with gracefully weeping, cord-like,
            golden-yellow foliage in short tufts and longer unbranched shoots.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cordyline australis</latin>
        <common>Cabbage Palm</common>
        <altname>Cabbage Tree</altname>
        <altname>Cabbage Palm</altname>
        <altname>Ti kouka</altname>
        <description>A widely branched monocot tree endemic to New Zealand, is is widely planted in
            gardens. In time this becomes a substantial tree.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Corylus avellana</latin>
        <common>Common Hazel</common>
        <description>A species of hazel native to Europe and western Asia, from the British Isles
            south to Iberia,Greece,Turkey and Cyprus, north to central Scandinavia, and east to the
            central Ural Mountains, the Caucasus, and northwestern Iran. It is an important
            component of the hedgerows that were the traditional field boundaries in lowland
            England. The wood was traditionally grown ascoppice, the poles cut being used for
            wattle-and-daub building and agricultural fencing.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cornus controversa</latin>
        <common>Dogwood</common>
        <description>A species of flowering plant in the genus Cornus of the dogwood family
            Cornaceae, native to China, the Himalayas and Japan. It is a deciduous tree growing to
            50 ft, with multiple tiered branches.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cornus controversa 'Variegata'</latin>
        <common>Table Dogwood</common>
        <altname>Wedding Cake Tree</altname>
        <description>A small deciduous tree with strongly tiered branches bearing narrowly ovate leaves broadly margined with cream and turning yellow in autumn. Small, cream flowers in flat clusters are followed by black berries.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Corylus colurna</latin>
        <common>Turkish Hazel</common>
        <description>A deciduous tree native to southeast Europe and southwest Asia, from the
            Balkans through northern Turkey to northern Iran. Its leaf and fruit are similar to the
            Hazel bush, but it makes a stout tree with very dark rough bark.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cornus kousa</latin>
        <common>Kousa Dogwood</common>
        <description>A small deciduous tree 812 m tall, in the family Cornaceae. Common names
            include Japanese dogwood, kousa, and kousa dogwood. Synonyms are Benthamia kousa and
            Cynoxylon kousa.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Corylus avellana 'Contorta'</latin>
        <common>Corkscrew Hazel</common>
        <description>A large deciduous shrub with highly contorted and twisted branches bearing broadly ovate leaves and pendent yellow male catkins in late winter and early spring; useful for winter flower arrangements.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Corylus maxima 'Purpurea'</latin>
        <common>Purple-leaved Filbert</common>
        <description>Corylus are deciduous trees and large shrubs with broad leaves, and showy male
            catkins in early spring, followed by edible nuts. 'Purpurea' is a large deciduous shrub
            to 6m, with broad, deep purple leaves to 12cm in length. Pendulous pale yellow catkins
            on leafless twigs in late winter are followed by edible nuts concealed by a tubular
            husk.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cotoneaster</latin>
        <common>Cotoneaster</common>
        <description>A genus of flowering plants in the rose family,Rosaceae,native to the
            Palaearctic region (temperate Asia, Europe, north Africa), with a strong concentration
            of diversity in the genus in the mountains of southwestern China and the Himalayas.They
            are related to hawthorns(Crataegus),firethorns(Pyracantha),photinias(Photinia)
            androwans(Sorbus).</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Crataegus monogyna</latin>
        <common>Common Hawthorn</common>
        <altname>Single-seeded Hawthorn</altname>
        <description>A species of hawthorn native to Europe, northwest Africa and western Asia. It
            has been introduced in many other parts of the world. It can be an invasive
            weed.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Crataegus persimilis 'Prunifolia'</latin>
        <common>Broad-leaved Cockspur Thorn 'Prunifolia'</common>
        <description>Crataegus are deciduous trees and shrubs, usually with spiny branches, lobed or
            toothed leaves, and clusters of creamy-white flowers followed by red or black fruits.
            Some have fine autumn colourA small, broad-crowned deciduous tree with long thorns and
            glossy broad-oval leaves. Dramatic red and orange autumn colour. Flowers white; fruits
            deep red</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Crataegus laevigata 'Paul's Scarlet'</latin>
        <common>Hawthorn 'Paul's Scarlet'</common>
        <description>Crataegus are deciduous trees and shrubs, usually with spiny branches, lobed or
            toothed leaves, and clusters of creamy-white flowers followed by red or black fruits.
            Some have fine autumn colour. 'Paul's Scarlet' is a small, rounded deciduous thorny tree
            with lobed, glossy leaves. Flowers fully double, light red.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Crataegus x lavalleei</latin>
        <common>Hybrid Cockspur Thorn</common>
        <parent>Crataegus mexicana</parent>
        <parent>Crataegus calpodendron</parent>
        <description>Crataegus are deciduous trees and shrubs, usually with spiny branches, lobed or toothed leaves, and clusters of creamy-white flowers followed by red or black fruits. Some have fine autumn colour.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cryptomeria japonica</latin>
        <common>Japanese Cedar</common>
        <altname>Sugi</altname>
        <description>A monotypic genus of conifer in the cypress family Cupressaceae, formerly
            belonging to the family Taxodiaceae. It includes only one species, Cryptomeria japonica.
            It is endemic to Japan, where it is known as sugi. Its most attractive feature is its
            red fibrous barks with long vertical striations.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cupressus macrocarpa</latin>
        <common>Monterey Cypress</common>
        <description>This species was first introduced into the UK from its tiny natural outpost on
            the Monterey Peninsula in Californian in 1839. It proved to have the fastest rate of
            growth of any species. It is one of the parents of Cupressus leylandii, so commonly, and
            rashly, planted as screening today.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cupressus sempervirens</latin>
        <common>Italian Cypress</common>
        <altname>Mediterranean Cypress</altname>
        <description>A species of cypress native to the eastern Mediterranean region, in northeast
            Libya, southern Albania, southern coastal Croatia, southern Greece. Now often planted in
            gardens, but old specimens are uncommon.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cupressus x leylandii</latin>
        <synomym>× Cuprocyparis leylandii</synomym>
        <common>Leylandii</common>
        <altname>Leyland cypress</altname>
        <parent>Cupressus macrocarpa</parent>
        <parent>Cupressus nootkatensis</parent>
        <description>A fast-growing coniferous evergreen tree much used in horticulture, primarily for hedges and screens. Even on sites of relatively poor culture, plants have been known to grow to heights of 15 metres (49 ft) in 16 years. Their rapid, thick growth means they are sometimes used to achieve privacy, but such use can result in disputes with neighbours whose own property becomes overshadowed. The tree is a hybrid, almost always sterile, and propagated mainly from cuttings.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Davidia involucrata</latin>
        <common>Dove Tree</common>
        <altname>Paper Handkerchief Tree</altname>
        <altname>Handkerchief Tree</altname>
        <altname>Pocket Handkerchief Tree</altname>
        <altname>Ghost Tree</altname>
        <description>A medium-sized deciduous tree in the dogwood family Cornaceae, subfamily
            Nyssoideae. When flowering, it has white bracts that cover the flowers in late
            May.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ehretia acuminata</latin>
        <common>Chinese Koda</common>
        <description>A deciduous tree found in Japan, China, Bhutan, Nepal, Laos, Vietnam, New
            Guinea and Australia. Fossil evidence suggests an ancient Laurasian
            origin.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Eucalyptus gunnii</latin>
        <common>Cider Gum</common>
        <altname>Eucalyptus Gunnii</altname>
        <altname>Gunnii</altname>
        <description>A species of flowering plant in the family Myrtaceae, endemic to Tasmania,
            occurring on the plains and slopes of the central plateaux to around 1100 metres, with
            isolated occurrences south of Hobart. This is very frequently planted in gardens, and
            has proved to be hardy. Very fast growing.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fagus sylvatica</latin>
        <common>European beech</common>
        <altname>Common Beech</altname>
        <description>A deciduous tree belonging to the beech family Fagaceae.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fagus sylvatica 'Fastigiata'</latin>
        <common>Pyramidal Beech</common>
        <altname>Common Beech</altname>
        <altname>European Beech</altname>
        <description>A deciduous tree belonging to the beech family Fagaceae.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fagus sylvatica 'Dawyck'</latin>
        <common>Dawyck Beech</common>
        <description>A large, fastigiate deciduous tree, becoming broadly columnar with age. Leaves
            green, elliptic, turning orange-brown in autumn. Flowers inconspicuous, fruit
            bristly.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fagus sylvatica 'Pendula'</latin>
        <common>Weeping Beech</common>
        <description>A cultured variety of the deciduous European Beech. The weeping beech is
            characterized by its shape with sweeping, pendulous branches.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fagus sylvatica 'Purpurea'</latin>
        <common>Copper Beech</common>
        <description>Atropurpurea Group are large deciduous trees grown for their deep purple
            leaves, which become reddish in autumn. In Spring the newly opened leaves have still
            fully to develop the 'copper' pigments that mask the normal green colour of beech trees.
            The male and female flowers of the beech are arranged in catkins. The male ones hang
            down, while the reddish hairy female catkins stand upright. The beech nuts develop from
            these female flowers. Good seed (nut) crops - called 'masts' only occur every four or
            five years.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fagus sylvatica var heterophylla 'Aspleniifolia'</latin>
        <common>Fern-leaf Beech</common>
        <description>A medium-sized deciduous tree with a broad, open crown. Leaves variable, mostly
            long and narrow, cut deeply into several pairs of pointed lobes and turning orange-brown
            in autumn This is a natural variant with cut leaves.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ficus carica</latin>
        <common>Fig</common>
        <description>An Asian species of flowering plants in the mulberry family, known as the
            common fig. It is the source of the fruit also called the fig, and as such is an
            important crop in those areas where it is grown commercially.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fraxinus angustifolia</latin>
        <common>Narrow-leaf Ash</common>
        <description>A species of Fraxinus native to central and southern Europe, northwest Africa,
            and southwest Asia. Widely planted in parks in recent years, it turns a magnificent
            purple in the autumn.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fraxinus excelsior</latin>
        <common>Ash</common>
        <altname>European Ash</altname>
        <altname>Common Ash</altname>
        <description>This is a native species and common to abundant in much of Britain. In 'A Field
            Guide to the Trees in Britain and Northern Europe' by Alan Mitchell, he describes the
            'total sexual confusion' shown by this species. 'Some trees are all male, some all
            female, some male with one or more female branches, some vice versa, some branches male
            one year and female the next. 536 species of lichen have been recorded growing on Ash
            trees in Britain. It is thought that Ash bark is particularly conducive to lichen
            colonisation because of its high pH - between 5.5 and 6.5 and its relatively open canopy
            which lets more light through to lower branches and trunk, which helps the lichens to
            photosynthesise more efficiently. Also, widespread instances of galls can be found on
            the Common Ash, Fraxinus excelsior. They are caused by Aceria fraxinivorus mites which
            attack the flowers soon after they open. At first the galls are green, but they soon
            turn brown. They can stay on the tree through the winter. The mites pass the winter in
            the galls or in crevices in the bark. But how long before 'Ash dieback' disease -
            Chalaria fraxina is found these trees. It could perhaps be identified as soon as the
            leaves emerge. Please be vigilant and check any ash trees and ash woodland which you
            manage for signs of this disease, especially trees planted within the past 20 years.
            Refer to the Forestry Commission video and pictorial guides on their website for help to
            recognise the symptoms (www.forestry.gov.uk/chalara). If you have concerns, please
            report them through the Tree Alert app or online form available at
            www.forestry.gov.uk/treealert, preferably including photos, so that the report can be
            assessed and followed up if necessary. An advisory note is attached which gives further
            information.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fraxinus excelsior 'Diversifolia'</latin>
        <common>One-leaved Ash</common>
        <description>This is a natural variant of the Ash in which the leaf is a single blade rather
            than leaflets. It was quite widely planted about 30 years ago.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fraxinus excelsior 'Pendula'</latin>
        <common>Weeping Ash</common>
        <description>A strong-growing medium-sized deciduous tree forming an umbrella-shaped crown
            of pendulous branches arching to the ground. Leaves pinnate, sometimes turning yellow in
            the autumn They were a Victorian cemetery favourite, achieved by grafting as high as
            possible, as the branches grow straight downwards.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fraxinus ornus</latin>
        <common>Flowering Ash</common>
        <altname>Manna Ash</altname>
        <description>Named for its dramatic white flowers in spring, this is a species of Fraxinus native to southern Europe and southwestern Asia, from Spain and Italy north to Austria, Poland and the Czech Republic, and east through the Balkans, Turkey, and western Syria to Lebanon and Armenia.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ginkgo biloba</latin>
        <common>Maidenhair Tree</common>
        <description>It has a very upright form of growth and is now being planted in streets. Its
            leaf is unlike that of any other tree, and it turns a wonderful lemon yellow in the
            Autumn. Called a living fossil by Darwin as it is the only existing species of a group
            of primitive trees that originated in, and was dominant in the Jurassic era, 200 million
            years ago. Fossils of the Jurassic trees are virtually identical to those of present day
            trees. Ginkgo biloba is the scientific name, 'Ginkgo' deriving from a Japanese word
            meaning 'silver plum' which refers to its fruits; 'biloba' describing the
            characteristically two lobed shape of the leaves. The tree is uncommon outside southern
            England and is most frequent around London and in the Bristol-Bath-Yeovil area. The
            Maidenhair Tree is probably a native of eastern Asia and the first specimen planted in
            this country is still at Kew, where it was brought from China in 1754. A relic
            population occurs in China, believed to be wild, though studies have shown little
            genetic variation in this population and it may be that these trees result from original
            plantings by local monks, taken from temple specimens. Nevertheless, some individuals in
            wild hill populations are believed to be up to 3000 years old. Trees are either male or
            female. Females bear fruits that when shed and begin to rot, produce a putrid smell. It
            has been postulated that this might have been an adaptation to attract carrion-feeding
            dinosaurs who would then aid dispersal via their digestive system. The fruits produce an
            oil source containing compounds with insecticidal properties. More than 40 components
            from the ginkgo tree have been identified, but only two are believed to act as medicine:
            flavonoids and terpenoids. Flavonoids are plant-based antioxidants. Laboratory and
            animal studies have shown that flavonoids protect the nerves, heart muscle, blood
            vessels, and retina from damage. Terpenoids (such as ginkgoilides) improve blood flow by
            dilating blood vessels and reducing the stickiness of platelets and ginkgoilides is also
            used in treating Parkinson's Disease. It had been thought that Ginkgo compounds
            extracted from the leaves could improve memory in older people but one of the longest
            and best-designed studies found ginkgo was no better than a placebo in reducing
            Alzheimer's symptoms. In a 2008 study, 176 people in the United Kingdom with Alzheimer's
            took either ginkgo or placebo for 6 months. At the end of the study there was no
            difference in mental function or quality of life between the groups. Another
            well-designed study in 2008 with more than 3,000 elderly participants also found the
            ginkgo was no better than placebo in preventing dementia or Alzheimer's.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Gleditsia triacanthos</latin>
        <common>Honey Locust</common>
        <description>This deciduous tree can grow to 20m and is native to the north and east of the United States. It arrived in Britain during the later half of the 17th century, at Fulham, London.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Griselinia littoralis</latin>
        <common>Kapuka</common>
        <altname>New Zealand Broadleaf</altname>
        <description>A fast-growing small to medium-sized evergreen tree growing up to 20 m tall,
            though generally 4-8 m particularly in coastal exposure, it is quite commonly used as a
            hedging plant.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Gymnocladus dioicus</latin>
        <common>Kentucky Coffee Tree</common>
        <description>A tree in the subfamily Caesalpinioideae of the pea family Fabaceae, native to
            the Midwest and Upper South of North America with leaves a yard long.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ilex</latin>
        <common>Holly</common>
        <description>A genus of 400 to 600 species of flowering plants in the family Aquifoliaceae,
            and the only living genus in that family. The species are evergreen or deciduous trees,
            shrubs, and climbers from tropics to temperate zones worldwide.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ilex aquifolium</latin>
        <common>English Holly</common>
        <altname>Common Holly</altname>
        <altname>European holly</altname>
        <description>A species of holly native to western and southern Europe, northwest Africa, and
            southwest Asia, hollies are very widespread but mostly form an understory because they
            are so tolerant of shade.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ilex aquifolium 'Argentea Marginata'</latin>
        <common>Silver-margined Holly</common>
        <description>A medium-sized evergreen tree of conical outline, with spiny, undulate leaves
            boldly edged with cream and tinged pink when young. Flowers small, dull white; berries
            bright red</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ilex aquifolium 'Aureomarginata'</latin>
        <common>Aureomarginata English Holly</common>
        <description/>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Juglans nigra</latin>
        <common>Black Walnut</common>
        <altname>Eastern Black Walnut</altname>
        <description>A species of deciduous tree in the walnut family, Juglandaceae, native to
            eastern North America species which looks superficially like an Ash. The fruit are
            inedible. It bears walnut-like fruits with no resemblence to the fruits of
            Wingnuts</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Juglans regia</latin>
        <common>Persian Walnut</common>
        <altname>Common Walnut</altname>
        <altname>English Walnut</altname>
        <description>Not often planted, but often self-sown by squirrels, a native of Asia from the
            Caucasus to Japan, valuable for their timber and for the excellent nuts. The ancient
            Greeks and Romans had walnut orchards, and it has been widely cultivated in Northern
            Europe since 1500. Its timber became a favourite for quality furniture from 1600 until
            it was replaced by mahogany. The English have long grown walnuts with optimism if not
            always with success, but ours seem to be flourishing. Sometimes it is called the English
            walnut, even though it is not a native tree and does not grow wild in Britain. It is at
            the northern edge of its range in Britain. With an increasingly warmer climate however,
            growing conditions are improving. Some nurseries are offering up to 30 different
            varieties of walnut, some chosen for their nuts, others give a better quality wood.
            Walnut wood is four times the value of oak wood. In the Park, the walnut's leaves are
            regularly attacked by eriophyoid mites - Acaria erinea, which induce erinia galls (dense
            patches of glandular hairs) in which the mites can feed safely. The mites only leave an
            erinium when the hairs collapse and the leaves dry out at the end of the
            summer.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Juniperus communis 'Compressa'</latin>
        <common>Chinese Juniper</common>
        <altname>Noah's ark Juniper</altname>
        <description>A dwarf evergreen conifer with attractive, light green foliage and white
            stomatal lines which form a narrow, upright cone-shaped mass.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Koelreuteria paniculata</latin>
        <common>Pride of India</common>
        <altname>Golden Rain Tree</altname>
        <altname>China Tree</altname>
        <altname>Varnish Tree</altname>
        <description>A species of flowering plant in the family Sapindaceae, native to eastern Asia,
            in China and Korea. It has bright yellow flowers which come in August, it has very
            unusual attractive leaves and small black fruit in papery bladders.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Larix</latin>
        <common>Larch</common>
        <description>Conifers in the genus Larix, in the family Pinaceae. Growing from 20 to 45 m
            tall (65 to 147ft),they are native to much of the cooler temperate northern hemisphere,
            on lowlands in the north and high on mountains further south. Larches are among the
            dominant plants in the boreal forests of Siberia and Canada.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Larix decidua</latin>
        <common>Larch</common>
        <altname>European Larch</altname>
        <description>A species of larch native to the mountains of central Europe, in the Alps and
            Carpathian Mountains, with disjunct lowland populations in northern Poland and southern
            Lithuania. Most of those planted grow rather badly.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Laurus nobilis</latin>
        <common>Bay tree</common>
        <description>An aromatic evergreen tree or large shrub with green, glossy leaves, native to
            the Mediterranean region. It is one of the plants used for bay leaf seasoning in
            cooking.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ligustrum lucidum</latin>
        <common>Chinese Privet</common>
        <altname>Broad-leaf Privet</altname>
        <altname>Glossy Privet</altname>
        <altname>Tree Privet</altname>
        <altname>Wax-leaf Privet</altname>
        <description>A flowering plant in the olive family, Oleaceae, native to the southern half of
            China and naturalized in many places: Spain, Italy, Algeria, Canary Islands, New
            Zealand, Lesotho, South Africa, Japan, Korea, Australia, Norfolk Island, Chiapas,
            Central America, Argentina, and the southern United States(California, Arizona,
            Maryland, and the southeast from Texas to North Carolina).The name</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Liquidambar styraciflua</latin>
        <common>Sweetgum</common>
        <altname>American sweetgum</altname>
        <altname>Sweet Gum</altname>
        <altname>Sweet-gum</altname>
        <altname>Hazel Pine</altname>
        <altname>American-storax</altname>
        <altname>Bilsted</altname>
        <altname>Red-gum</altname>
        <altname>Satin-walnut</altname>
        <altname>Star-leaved Gum</altname>
        <altname>Alligator-wood</altname>
        <description>A deciduous tree in the genus Liquidambar native to warm temperate areas of
            eastern North America and tropical montane regions of Mexico and Central America. Sweet
            gum is one of the main valuable forest trees in the southeastern United States, and is a
            popular ornamental tree in temperate climates. It is recognizable by the combination of
            its five-pointed star-shaped leaves and its hard, spiked fruits. It is currently
            classified in the plant family Altingiaceae, but was formerly considered a member of the
            Hamamelidaceae.Has magnificent autumn colouring and leaves rather like a Maple. Rare,
            but increasingly planted.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Liquidambar styraciflua 'Worplesdon'</latin>
        <common>Sweet Gum 'Worplesdon'</common>
        <description>A broad-crowned medium-sized deciduous tree with five-lobed, maple-like leaves which turn to deep orange and yellow in autumn. Flowers insignificant.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Liriodendron tulipifera</latin>
        <common>Tulip Tree</common>
        <description>The Western Hemisphere representative of the two-species genus Liriodendron,
            and the tallest eastern hardwood. It is native to eastern North America from Southern
            Ontario and Illinois eastward to southeastern Massachusetts and Rhode Island, and south
            to central Florida and Louisiana. It can grow to more than 50 m (160 ft) in virgin cove
            forests of the Appalachian Mountains, often with no limbs until it reaches 25?30 m
            (80?100 ft) in height, making it a very valuable timber tree. It is fast-growing,
            without the common problems of weak wood strength and short lifespan often seen in
            fast-growing species. April marks the start of the flowering period in the southern USA;
            trees at the northern limit of cultivation begin to flower in June. The flowers are pale
            green or yellow (rarely white), with an orange band on the tepals; they yield large
            quantities of nectar. Named after its Tulip shaped greenish flowers and recognisable by
            its leaves that appear to have had the tips bitten out of them, it is a handsome and
            fast growing tree, widely planted for many years.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Lophozonia obliqua</latin>
        <common>Roble Beech</common>
        <description>A deciduous tree from Chile and Argentina. It grows from 33 to 43 south
            latitude. The northern extent of this tree's range in Chile is considered to be the
            Vizcachas Mountains and La Campana National Park. This is the beech of South America and
            it is too rarely planted in Bristol. The tree in the Zoo has a girth of
            200cm.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Magnolia</latin>
        <common>magnolia</common>
        <description>A large genus of about 210 flowering plant species in the subfamily
            Magnolioideae of the family Magnoliaceae. It is named after French botanist Pierre
            Magnol. Magnolia is an ancient genus.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Magnolia grandiflora</latin>
        <common>Bull Bay</common>
        <altname>Southern Magnolia</altname>
        <description>A tree of the family Magnoliaceae native to the southeastern United States,
            from coastal North Carolina to central Florida, and west to East Texas and Oklahoma. The
            evergreen magnolia from the southern states of the USA which has flowers the size of
            dinner plates.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Malus sylvestris</latin>
        <common>European Crab Apple</common>
        <description>A species of the genus Malus, native to Europe. Its scientific name
            means</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Mespilus germanica</latin>
        <common>Medlar</common>
        <altname>Common Medlar</altname>
        <description>A large shrub or small tree, and the name of the fruit of this
            tree.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Metasequoia glyptostroboides</latin>
        <common>Dawn Redwood</common>
        <description>A fast-growing, endangered coniferous tree, the sole living species of the
            genus Metasequoia, one of three species in the subfamily Sequoioideae. This tree was
            discovered at a remote site in China in 1941, and widely distributed to parks across the
            world.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Morus alba</latin>
        <common>White Mulberry</common>
        <description>A short-lived, fast-growing, small to medium-sized mulberry tree, which grows
            to 1020 m tall. The species is native to northern China, and is widely cultivated and
            naturalized elsewhere.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Morus nigra</latin>
        <common>Black Mulberry</common>
        <altname>Blackberry</altname>
        <description>A species of flowering plant in the family Moraceae, native to southwestern
            Asia, where it has been cultivated for so long that its precise natural range is
            unknown. This species is widely planted for its delicious fruit, but is very often found
            growing horizontally.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Neolitsea sericea</latin>
        <common>Neolitsea sericea</common>
        <description>A species of a medium-sized evergreen tree up to 10 m tall in the Lauraceae
            family. It is found in China, Taiwan, south Korea, and Japan. A very rare tree. It is
            evergreen, and not especially impressive. It is multi-trunked, and related to
            Laurel.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ostrya carpinifolia</latin>
        <common>Hop Hornbeam</common>
        <altname>European Hop-hornbeam</altname>
        <description>A tree in the family Betulaceae. It is the only species of the genus Ostrya
            that is native to Europe. This is a rare tree closely related to the Hornbeam, with
            fruit that look like a bunch of ripe hops.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Parrotia persica</latin>
        <common>Persian Ironwood</common>
        <description>A deciduous tree in the family Hamamelidaceae, closely related to the witch-hazel genus Hamamelis. It is native to northern Iran and other parts of Iran and it is endemic in the Alborz mountains. This is a large, sprawling tree, with dark leaves that turn a wonderful purple in the autumn. It is rare.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Paulownia tomentosa</latin>
        <common>Foxglove Tree</common>
        <description>A deciduous tree in the family Paulowniaceae, native to central and western
            China. Paulownia tomentosa is an extremely fast-growing tree, and is a persistent exotic
            invasive in North America with huge leaves and wonderful purple flowers on the bare
            branches in early spring.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Phillyrea latifolia</latin>
        <common>Phillyrea</common>
        <altname>Green Olive Tree</altname>
        <altname>Mock Privet</altname>
        <description>A rare small evergreen tree which is a species of tree in the family
            Oleaceae.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Picea abies</latin>
        <common>Norway Spruce</common>
        <description>A species of spruce native to Northern, Central and Eastern Europe. It has
            branchlets that typically hang downwards, and the largest cones of any spruce, 9?17 cm
            long. This is the commonest Christmas Tree.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Picea breweriana</latin>
        <common>Brewer's Spruce</common>
        <altname>Brewer's Weeping Spruce</altname>
        <altname>Weeping Spruce</altname>
        <description>A species of spruce native to western North America, where it is one of the
            rarest on the continent, endemic to the Klamath Mountains of southwest Oregon and
            northwest California. The specific epithet breweriana is in honor of the American
            botanist William Henry Brewer. Spruces are uncommon in Bristol. This species has
            branches hung with pendulous branchlets.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pinus</latin>
        <common>pine</common>
        <description>Any conifer in the genus Pinus of the family Pinaceae. Pinus is
            the sole genus in the subfamily Pinoideae.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pinus jeffreyi</latin>
        <common>Jefferies Pine</common>
        <altname>Yellow Pine</altname>
        <altname>Black Pine</altname>
        <description>A North American pine tree mainly found in California, but also in the
            westernmost part of Nevada, southwestern Oregon, and northern Baja California. This tree
            has the distinction of carrying the largest pine cone, up to 500 grams in weight, and
            the longest needles, up to 23cm. of any pine. It is very rare in Bristol.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pinus nigra</latin>
        <common>European Black Pine</common>
        <altname>Black Pine</altname>
        <altname>Austrian Pine</altname>
        <altname>Corsican Pine</altname>
        <description>It is a native of South-eastern Europe and commonly occurs on limestone. The
            needles occur in pairs and although it is an evergreen species, the ground under the
            trees is covered with shed needles in November. Its cones, which contain the seeds, can
            be found on the ground at almost any time of the year. The most common and successful
            pine in the city. It was widely planted on the Downs in the 1880s.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pinus pinaster</latin>
        <common>Maritime Pine</common>
        <altname>Cluster Pine</altname>
        <description>A pine native to Mediterranean region, this species is distinguished by holding
            its unopened cones on its branches for years, waiting for a fire to come to open
            them.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pinus sylvestris</latin>
        <common>Scots Pine</common>
        <description>A species of pine that is native to Eurasia, ranging from Western Europe to
            Eastern Siberia, south to the Caucasus Mountains and Anatolia, and north to well inside
            the Arctic Circle in Scandinavia. This is quite often planted, but rarely does well in
            Bristol.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pinus wallichiana</latin>
        <common>Bhutan Pine</common>
        <description>A coniferous evergreen tree native to the Himalaya, Karakoram and Hindu Kush
            mountains, from eastern Afghanistan east across northern Pakistan and India to Yunnan in
            southwest China. This tree has very graceful fine needles in bunches of five, and is
            often planted.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Platanus orientalis</latin>
        <common>Eastern Plane</common>
        <description>A large, deciduous tree of the Platanaceae family, growing to 30 m or more, and
            known for its longevity and spreading crown. It is one of the parents of the London
            Plane, but is now very rarely planted, though it grows just as fast.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Platanus orientalis var insularis</latin>
        <common>Cyprian Plane</common>
        <description>An interesting variety with leaves that have five long fingers, and holds its
            foliage later than other planes.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Platanus x acerifolia</latin>
        <synomym>Platanus x hispanica</synomym>
        <common>London Plane</common>
        <altname>Hybrid Plane</altname>
        <parent>Platanus orientalis</parent>
        <parent>Platanus occidentalis</parent>
        <description>London Plane is 'allegedly' a cross between the Oriental Plane and the American Plane. The hybrid probably arose in Southern France, and seed sent from Montpelier was first raised at Oxford Botanic Garden around 1670. It is a much more adaptable and frost-resistant tree than the parental species and has, as a consequence, become widely distributed throughout much of central Europe. The London Planes can be easily identified by the mosaic-like appearance of their bark, which develops as the bark peels off in large flakes to leave, initially, pale yellow patches of the inner bark below. London Planes are particularly tolerant of smoke and dust laden air of cities. This is doubtless why so many London Planes were planted in our park. The Victorian air in Bristol must have been quite noxious from all the domestic coal fires emitting copious quantities of smoke and fumes. In autumn and winter, when the leaves have dropped, the globose clusters of fruits are clearly visible, hanging from long stalks in clusters of two or three. In winter, these provide a valuable food source for goldfinches and greenfinches which can commonly be seen feeding on them. In spring,the globose female catkins appear, their tips a pinkish red.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Populus alba</latin>
        <common>White Poplar</common>
        <altname>Silver Poplar</altname>
        <altname>Abele</altname>
        <description>A species of poplar, most closely related to the aspens. It is native from
            Morocco and the Iberian Peninsula through central Europe to central Asia. This tree
            suckers vigorously, and can often be seen along Motorways. The undersides of the leaves
            are white and turn silver in the Autumn.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Populus nigra 'Italica'</latin>
        <common>Lombardy Poplar</common>
        <description>A large, vigorous, narrowly columnar deciduous tree to 30m tall, with bright
            green ovate leaves and crimson male catkins before the leaves open in early spring.
            Poplars are exceptionally fast growing trees, but there are very few old Lombardy
            Poplars in Bristol parks, though they were often planted as industrial screening in the
            1930s.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Populus nigra 'Plantierensis'</latin>
        <common>Black Poplar</common>
        <description>The following information is taken verbatim from the entry on Black Poplar in
            Wikipedia: The Plantierensis group consists of clones derived by crossing 'Italica' with
            P. nigra ssp betulifolia at the Plantires Nursery near Metz in France in 1884; they are
            similar to 'Italica' (and often mistaken for it) but with a slightly broader crown, and
            better adapted to the cool, humid climate of northwest Europe, where the true Lombardy
            poplar does not grow well. Both male and female clones are grown. This is the tree most
            commonly grown in Great Britain and Ireland as 'Lombardy poplar'.' So, if you are not
            even more confused, this tree is not a true Lombardy Poplar (Populus nigra 'Italica')
            but Populus nigra 'Plantierensis' which is still (mistakenly) referred to as the
            'Lombardy' Poplar! This view is supported by the fact that Black Poplars were commonly
            planted in parks in Victorian times.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Populus trichocarpa</latin>
        <common>Balsam Poplar</common>
        <altname>Black cottonwood</altname>
        <altname>Western Balsam-poplar</altname>
        <altname>California Poplar</altname>
        <description>A deciduous broadleaf tree species native to western North America. It is used
            for timber, and is notable as a model organism in plant biology. This fine species, with
            a strongly upright growth, scents the whole area with balsam when its buds break in the
            spring, and it turns a magnificent yellow in the Autumn. It is not common.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Populus x canadensis</latin>
        <common>Hybrid Black Poplar</common>
        <altname>Black Poplar</altname>
        <altname>Canadian Poplar</altname>
        <altname>Carolina Poplar</altname>
        <parent>Populus nigra</parent>
        <parent>Populus deltoides</parent>
        <description>A naturally occurring hybrid of Populus nigra and Populus deltoides. It is commonly used by landscape architects. Varieties include</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Populus x canescens</latin>
        <common>Grey Poplar</common>
        <parent>Populus alba</parent>
        <parent>Populus tremula</parent>
        <description>A hybrid between Populus alba and Populus tremula. It is intermediate between its parents, with a thin grey downy coating on the leaves, which are also much less deeply lobed than the leaves of P. albus Distinguished by the black diamond shaped pits on its trunk.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus</latin>
        <common>Cherry</common>
        <description>A genus of trees and shrubs, which includes the plums, cherries, peaches,
            nectarines, apricots and almonds. Around 430 species are spread throughout the northern
            temperate regions of the globe.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus avium</latin>
        <common>Wild Cherry</common>
        <altname>Sweet Cherry</altname>
        <altname>Gean</altname>
        <altname>Bird Cherry</altname>
        <description>A species of cherry native to Europe, Anatolia, Maghreb, and western Asia, from the British Isles south to Morocco and Tunisia, north to the Trondheimsfjord region in Norway and east to the Caucasus and northern Iran, with a small isolated population in the western Himalaya. The species is widely cultivated in other regions and has become naturalized in North America and Australia. It seeds itself readily, and spreads by suckering. They turn a fine colour in the autumn.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus cerasifera 'Atropurpurea'</latin>
        <common>Myrobalan Plum</common>
        <description>The English name indicates the tree bears plum fruits, though they are small
            and resemble cherries in both shape and colour. The fruit was once used in making
            ointments and the alternative name of 'Myrobalan' comes from two Greek words, myron
            meaning sweet-scented ointment and balanos, a fruit.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus cerasifera 'Pissardii'</latin>
        <common>Cherry Plum</common>
        <altname>Purple-leaved Plum</altname>
        <description>A small, ornamental plum tree with rich, dark-purple leaves displayed on
            blackish stems, against which the pink buds and blush/white flowers that appear in
            spring are a beautiful contrast. The flowers are followed by plum like fruits (not
            edible to humans) in the autumn, so extending the period of interest. With a rounded
            habit, the eventual height and spread of this Purple Leaved Plum tree after 20 years is
            about 5 x 4 metres.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus serrulata 'Kanzan'</latin>
        <common>Flowering Cherry 'Kanzan'</common>
        <description>A flowering cherry cultivar. It is a deciduous tree that grows to between 8 and 12 metres high with an 8-metre spread. Young trees have a vase-shaped habit that becomes more spreading into maturity.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus laurocerasus</latin>
        <common>Cherry Laurel,Common Laurel,English Laurel</common>
        <description>An evergreen species of cherry (Prunus), native to regions bordering theBlack
            Sea in southwestern Asiaand southeasternEurope, from Albania and Bulgaria east through Turkey to
            the Caucasus Mountains and northern Iran. </description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus lusitanica</latin>
        <common>Portuguese Laurel</common>
        <description>A species of the genus Prunus, related to the cherry. It is native to
            southwestern France, Spain, Portugal, Morocco, and Macaronesia.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus padus</latin>
        <common>Bird Cherry</common>
        <altname>Mayday Tree</altname>
        <description>The Bird Cherry is a native species but is only found in the wild in the
            Scottish glens where it is common and by streams in limestone areas in North West
            Yorkshire and in mid Wales. The specimens we have are a cultivar, P. pardus Watereri
            which flowers more profusely than the wild form of the tree. The flower spikes (racemes)
            are particularly long in 'Watereri' and the park trees come into spectacular flowering
            in late April, early May. The flowers are heavily scented. A trip to the park when the
            trees are in full flower is strongly recommended as the air around the trees is fragrant
            with their perfume. The name, Bird Cherry derives from the small fruits that ripen in
            August into bitter tasting 'cherries' which are only attractive to birds.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus serrulata</latin>
        <common>Japanese Cherry</common>
        <altname>Tibetan Cherry</altname>
        <altname>Hill Cherry</altname>
        <altname>Oriental Cherry</altname>
        <altname>East Asian Cherry</altname>
        <description>A species of cherry native to Japan, Korea and China and is used for its spring
            cherry blossom displays and festivals. There are a huge variety of varieties that the
            Japanese originally bred, and they are widely planted in streets and parks. The double
            pink Kanzan is well known. A small slow growing tree recognised at once by its bight
            glossy dark brown bark.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pseudotsuga menziesii</latin>
        <common>Douglas Fir</common>
        <description>A native to western North America, it is uncommon, and does not grow
            well.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pterocarya fraxinifolia</latin>
        <common>Caucasian Wingnut</common>
        <altname>Caucasian Walnut</altname>
        <description>A species of tree in the Juglandaceae family. It is native to the Caucasian
            region Armenia, Azerbaijan, Georgia, Iran, Russia, Ukraine and Turkey. Rarely planted
            for the good reason that is suckers spread very vigorously.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pyrus calleryana 'Chanticleer'</latin>
        <common>Chanticleer pear</common>
        <description>A narrowly conical medium-sized deciduous tree with glossy dark green ovate leaves, usually colouring well in autumn. Abundant clusters of white flowers followed by small brown fruits</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus</latin>
        <common>Oak</common>
        <description>A tree or shrub in the genus Quercus of the beech family, Fagaceae. There are
            approximately 600 extant species of oaks. The common name</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus alba</latin>
        <common>White Oak</common>
        <description>One of the pre-eminent hardwoods of eastern and central North America. This is
            a rare tree.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus borealis</latin>
        <common>Red Oak</common>
        <altname>Northern Red Oak</altname>
        <altname>Champion Oak</altname>
        <description>An oak in the red oak group (Quercus section Lobatae). It is a native of North
            America, in the eastern and central United States and southeast and south-central
            Canada. It grows from the north end of the Great Lakes, east to Nova Scotia, south as
            far as Georgia, Alabama, and Louisiana, and west to Oklahoma, Kansas, Nebraska, and
            Minnesota. It has been introduced to small areas in Western Europe, where it can
            frequently be seen cultivated in gardens and parks. It prefers good soil that is
            slightly acidic. This is a fast growing oak, with splendid colour in some autumns and
            very large leaves with fine points.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus castaneifolia</latin>
        <common>Chestnut-leaved Oak</common>
        <description>A species of oak in the turkey oak section Quercus sect. Cerris. It is native
            to the Caucasus and Alborz mountains of Iran, and resembles the closely related Turkey
            Oak in appearance.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus cerris</latin>
        <common>Turkey Oak</common>
        <altname>Austrian Oak</altname>
        <description>An oak native to south-eastern Europe and Asia Minor. It is the type species of
            Quercus sect. It has been widely planted, and is now spreading fast naturally though
            woodlands. It is distinguished by hairs at the tip of its buds, and the sharp teething
            on its leaves, but it is very variable.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus ilex</latin>
        <common>Holm Oak</common>
        <altname>Holly Oak</altname>
        <description>A large evergreen oak native to the Mediterranean region. It takes its name
            from holm, an ancient name for holly.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus libani</latin>
        <common>Lebanon Oak</common>
        <description>A species of oak native to the eastern Mediterranean in western Asia, including
            in Lebanon, western Syria, northeastern Israel, eastern Turkey, and northern Iraq and
            Iran.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus petraea</latin>
        <common>Sessile Oak</common>
        <altname>Durmast Oak</altname>
        <description>A species of oak tree native to most of Europe and into Anatolia and Iran. The
            sessile oak is an unofficial emblem in Wales and Cornwall.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus robur</latin>
        <common>Pedunculate Oak</common>
        <altname>Common Oak</altname>
        <altname>English Oak</altname>
        <description>A species of flowering plant in the beech and oak family Fagaceae. It is native
            to most of Europe west of the Caucasus.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus robur 'Cristata'</latin>
        <common>Cluster Oak</common>
        <description>The rarest tree in Bristol as there are only about six in the country. The
            original tree was found in Savernake Forest, and it is a very slow growing sport with
            distorted leaves. It does however come true from seed.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus robur 'Fastigiata'</latin>
        <common>Cypress Oak</common>
        <description>This variety grows in a columnar form, but is not often planted.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus rubra</latin>
        <common>Red Oak,Norther Red Oak</common>
        <description>An oak in the red oak group. It is a native of North America, in the eastern
            and central United States and southeast and south-central Canada.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus suber</latin>
        <common>Cork Oak</common>
        <description>A medium-sized, evergreen oak tree in the section Quercus sect. Cerris. It is
            the primary source of cork for wine bottle stoppers and other uses, such as cork
            flooring.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus x hispanica</latin>
        <common>Luccombe Oak</common>
        <parent>Quercus suber</parent>
        <parent>Quercus serris</parent>
        <description>This is a cross between Turkey Oak and Cork oak, and originated in the Exeter nurseries, and was widely planted by the Victorians. It does come true from seed. Most of the old estates had one, but they have tended to die in recent years.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus x turneri</latin>
        <common>Turner's Oak</common>
        <parent>Quercus robur</parent>
        <parent>Quercus ilex</parent>
        <description>This is a rare hybrid between the Common Oak and the Holm oak, which is semi-evergreen.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Robinia pseudoacacia</latin>
        <common>Robinia</common>
        <altname>False Acacia</altname>
        <altname>Black Locust</altname>
        <description>A medium-sized deciduous tree native to the southeastern United States, but it
            has been widely planted and naturalized elsewhere in temperate North America, Europe,
            Southern Africa and Asia and is considered an invasive species in some areas. It was
            introduced into Britain in 1636. This is a very tough spiny fast-growing tree that
            suckers readily, and has delicate white pea like flowers.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Salix</latin>
        <common>Willow,Sallows,Osiers</common>
        <description>Form the genus Salix, around 400 species of deciduous trees and shrubs, found
            primarily on moist soils in cold and temperate regions of the Northern
            Hemisphere.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Salix alba</latin>
        <common>White Willow</common>
        <description>A species of willow native to Europe and western and central Asia. The name
            derives from the pale under-surface of the leaves, this has a variety of attractive
            forms.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Salix caprea</latin>
        <common>Goat</common>
        <description>A common species of willow native to Europe and western and central Asia. It is
            a deciduous shrub or small tree, reaching a height of 8-10 m, rarely to 13
            m.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Salix fragilis</latin>
        <common>Crack Willow</common>
        <altname>Brittle Willow</altname>
        <description>A species of willow native to Europe and Western Asia. Distinguished by the
            fact that branchlets snap off, it is a very common native tree, but rare in
            parks.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Salix x sepulcralis 'Chrysocoma'</latin>
        <common>Weeping Golden Willow</common>
        <parent>Salix alba</parent>
        <parent>Salix babylonica</parent>
        <description>A familiar form that grows very rapidly, it is the most popular and widely grown weeping tree in the warm temperate regions of the world. It is an artificial hybrid between S. alba 'Vitellina' and S. babylonica.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sambucus nigra</latin>
        <common>Elder</common>
        <description>A species complex of flowering plants in the family Adoxaceae native to most of
            Europe and North America. Common names include elder, elderberry, black elder, European
            elder, European elderberry and European black elderberry.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sequoia sempervirens</latin>
        <common>Redwood</common>
        <altname>Coast Redwood</altname>
        <altname>California Redwood</altname>
        <description>The sole living species of the genus Sequoia in the cypress family
            Cupressaceae. Distinguished by its thick red bark and yew-like leaves, it does not grow
            as well as the Wellingtonia. It will coppice, which is very unusual for a
            conifer.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sequoiadendron giganteum</latin>
        <common>Wellingtonia</common>
        <description>The sole living species in the genus Sequoiadendron, and one of three species
            of coniferous trees known as redwoods, classified in the family Cupressaceae in the
            subfamily Sequoioideae, together with Sequoia sempervirens (coast redwood) and
            Metasequoia glyptostroboides (dawn redwood). The common use of the name</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sophora japonica</latin>
        <common>Scholar's Tree</common>
        <altname>Japanese Pagoda Tree</altname>
        <description>An uncommon tree that flowers in August, it is a species of tree in the
            subfamily Faboideae of the pea family Fabaceae. It was formerly included within a
            broader interpretation of the genus Sophora.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sorbus aria</latin>
        <common>Common Whitebeam</common>
        <altname>Whitebeam</altname>
        <description>Members of the Rosaceae family, comprising subgenus Aria of genus Sorbus, and hybrids involving species of this subgenus and members of subgenera Sorbus, Torminaria and Chamaemespilus. Many specimens on the face of the Avon Gorge, and a total of 19 micro-species have also been proved to be present there. A wide variety of species and variants are planted. The tree was often planted as boundary markers as the white underside of its leaves flashing in the wind drew attention to it.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sorbus aucuparia</latin>
        <common>Mountain Ash</common>
        <altname>Mountain-ash</altname>
        <altname>Rowan</altname>
        <description>A native small tree, and a number of varieties and species are often planted in gardens and car parks, but rarely in parks, it is a species of deciduous tree or shrub in the rose family.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sorbus bristoliensis</latin>
        <common>Bristol Whitebeam</common>
        <description>A species of flowering plant in the family Rosaceae. An endemic species of
            Whitebeam, unique to the Avon Gorge and there are estimated to be about 300 of them
            growing there. An unusual feature of this tree is that it quite often divides into two
            main trunks as it develops. Although that doesn't always happen, the development of a
            forked trunk is common. Trying to identify the Bristol Whitebeam from other Sorbus
            species in the Avon Gorge woodlands is not easy. Examining and comparing the particular
            shape of its fruits - orange berries - is the most reliable way an experienced botanist
            can recognise and differentiate the Bristol Whitebeam from other Sorbus.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sorbus hupehensis</latin>
        <common>Hubei Rowan</common>
        <description>A species of rowan native to central and western China. It is a small deciduous
            tree growing to 5o?=10 m tall, with grey-brown to purplish-brown bark. The branches and
            shoots are slender.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sorbus intermedia</latin>
        <common>Swedish Whitebeam</common>
        <description>A species of whitebeam found in southern Sweden, with scattered occurrences in
            easternmost Denmark, the far southwest of Finland, Estonia, Latvia and northern Poland.
            Widely planted often as a street tree but it tends to be short-lived.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sorbus aucuparia 'Joseph Rock'</latin>
        <common>Mountain Ash 'Joseph Rock'</common>
        <description>Sorbuscan be deciduous trees or shrubs with simple or pinnate leaves and clusters of small white or pink flowers, followed by white, yellow, pink, red or brown berries; some have fine autumn colour. 'Joseph Rock' is an upright tree with pinnate leaves which turn orange, red and purple in autumn, contrasting with the butter-yellow berries.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sorbus torminalis</latin>
        <common>Service Tree</common>
        <altname>Wild Service Tree</altname>
        <altname>Chequers</altname>
        <altname>Checker Tree</altname>
        <description>A species of Sorbus native to Europe from England and Wales east to Denmark and
            Poland, south to northwest Africa, and southeast to southwest Asia from Asia Minor to
            the Caucasus and Alborz mountains.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Taxus baccata</latin>
        <common>English Yew</common>
        <altname>Yew</altname>
        <description>A very common native tree, and the Irish form whose branches grow vertically is
            the commonest planted especially in cemeteries. The champion tree is on the Downs with a
            girth of 480cm. A conifer native to western, central and southern Europe, northwest
            Africa, northern Iran and southwest Asia.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Taxus baccata 'Fastigiata'</latin>
        <common>Irish Yew</common>
        <altname>Blue John</altname>
        <description>A large, bushy, upright evergreen shrub, columnar when young, later broader,
            with erect shoots bearing radially arranged, dark green leaves</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Tetradium daniellii</latin>
        <common>Korean Euodia</common>
        <altname>Bee-bee Tree</altname>
        <description>A species of flowering plant in the Rutaceae family. This is a rare tree that
            flowers in September.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Thuja occidentalis 'Rheingold'</latin>
        <common>Eastern arborvitae cultivar, White Cedar 'Rheingold'</common>
        <description>A slow-growing bushy evergreen conifer making a medium-sized shrub of ovoid outline. Bronze-tinged, amber-yellow foliage, becoming more richly-coloured in winter</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Thuja plicata</latin>
        <common>Western Red Cedar</common>
        <altname>Pacific Red Cedar</altname>
        <altname>Giant Arborvitae</altname>
        <altname>Western Arborvitae</altname>
        <altname>Giant Cedar</altname>
        <altname>Shinglewood</altname>
        <description>A species of Thuja, an evergreen coniferous tree in the cypress family
            Cupressaceae native to western North America. A handsome common conifer with a
            distinctive egg shaped fruit, it often has branches coming horizontally from the base of
            its trunk.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Tilia</latin>
        <common>Lime</common>
        <description>Tilia is a genus of about 30 species of trees native throughout most of the
            temperate Northern Hemisphere. Commonly called lime trees in the British Isles, they are
            not closely related to the lime fruit.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Tilia cordata</latin>
        <common>Small Leafed Lime</common>
        <description>A species of Tilia native to much of Europe, from Britain through central
            Fennoscandia, to central Russia, and south to central Spain, Italy, Greece, Bulgaria,
            Romania, Turkey, the Caucasus, and western Asia. Developing flower buds on Small Leafed
            Lime in Spring have leaf-like winged bracts which are later used to help disperse the
            seeds. Though nationally this is an uncommon native species, locally it is frequent with
            some very ancient trees in Leigh Woods. It rarely produces seed in our present climate.
            It is distinguished by holding its flowers and fruit upright rather than hanging. Many
            were planted on the Downs avenues to replace Huntingdon Elms.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Tilia platyphyllos</latin>
        <common>Large Leaved Lime</common>
        <description>A species of flowering plant in the family Malvaceae. It is a deciduous tree,
            native to much of Europe, including locally in southwestern Great Britain, growing on
            lime-rich soils. This a rare native species, but now very widely planted. It has none of
            the Common Lime's faults and all its advantages. Like all limes it is slow
            growing.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Tilia tomentosa</latin>
        <common>Silver Lime</common>
        <altname>Silver Linden</altname>
        <description>A species of flowering plant in the family Malvaceae, native to southeastern
            Europe and southwestern Asia, from Hungary A fine well shaped tree distinguished by the
            white undersides of the leaves.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Tilia tomentosa 'Petiolaris'</latin>
        <common>Silver Pendent Lime</common>
        <description>A vigorous and elegant large deciduous tree with pendulous branches bearing
            heart-shaped dark green leaves whitish beneath. Clusters of highly scented yellowish
            flowers are narcotic to bees Always grafted this is similar to the Silver Lime, but with
            a weeping form.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Tilia x europaea</latin>
        <common>Common Lime</common>
        <altname>European Lime</altname>
        <parent>Tilia cordata</parent>
        <parent>Tilia platyphyllos</parent>
        <description>A naturally occurring hybrid between Tilia cordata and Tilia platyphyllos. The Common Lime was the commonest tree for formal avenues in the 18th century. The trees typically have dense masses of growth both around the base of the trunk and in the middle of the tree as they are clones. Is easily coppiced.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ulmus glabra</latin>
        <common>Wych Elm</common>
        <altname>Scots Elm</altname>
        <description>Has the widest range of the European elm species, from Ireland eastwards to the
            Urals, and from the Arctic Circle south to the mountains of the Peloponnese in Greece;
            it is also found in Iran. Until 1975 Elms were the most familiar of trees, and the
            recovery from Dutch Elm Disease has been slow.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ulmus 'New Horizon'</latin>
        <common>Resistant Elm</common>
        <description>An American hybrid cultivar raised by the Wisconsin Alumni Research
            Foundation(WARF), from a crossing of the Japanese Elm clone W43-8 ='Reseda'(female parent)
            with Siberian Elm clone W426 grown from seed collected from a street tree at Yankton, South
            Dakota. 'New Horizon' was patented in the USA in 1994, while in Europe, it is one of
            the 'Resista' elms protected under E U breeders' rights (E U council decision
            2100/94).</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ulmus 'Sapporo Autumn Gold'</latin>
        <common>Resistant Elm</common>
        <description>One of the most commercially successful hybrid elm cultivars ever marketed,
            widely planted across North America and western Europe, although it has now been largely
            supplanted by more recent introductions.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Zelkova</latin>
        <common>Zelkova</common>
        <description>A genus of six species of deciduous trees in the elm family Ulmaceae, native to
            southern Europe, and southwest and eastern Asia. They vary in size from shrubs to large
            trees up to 35 m tall.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Zelkova serrata</latin>
        <common>Keaki</common>
        <description>A species of flowering plant native to Japan, Korea, eastern China and Taiwan,
            this is an uncommon Japanese tree. It is often grown as an ornamental tree, and used in
            bonsai.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Zelkova carpinifolia</latin>
        <common>Zelkova</common>
        <description>A species of Zelkova, native to the Caucasus, Kakar, and Alborz mountains in
            the extreme southeast of Europe and southwest Asia.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer campestre</latin>
        <common>Field Maple</common>
        <description>A deciduous, flowering tree in the soapberry and lychee family Sapindaceae. It is native to much of Europe, the British Isles, southwest Asia from Turkey to the Caucasus, and north Africa in the Atlas Mountains. it has been widely planted, and is introduced outside its native range in Europe, and to areas of USA and Western Australia with suitable climate.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer cappadocicum</latin>
        <common>Cappadocian Maple</common>
        <description>Cappadocian maple is grown as an ornamental tree in Europe. Many of the trees in cultivation show a strong tendency to produce numerous root sprouts, a character rare in maples</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fraxinus excelsior 'Aurea'</latin>
        <common>Golden Ash</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Malus</latin>
        <common>Apple</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus coccinea</latin>
        <common>Scarlet Oak</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Betula</latin>
        <common>Birch</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fraxinus excelsior 'Diversifoli'</latin>
        <common>One-leaved Ash</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus avium 'Plena'</latin>
        <common>Wild Cherry 'Plena'</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer pseudoplatanus 'Purpureum'</latin>
        <common>Purple Sycamore Maple</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sorbus</latin>
        <common>Sorbus</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pyrus</latin>
        <common>Pear</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ilex aquifolium 'Albomarginata'</latin>
        <common>White-margined Holly</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Fagus sylvatica 'Rohanii'</latin>
        <common>Rohanii European Beech</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer capillipes</latin>
        <common>Kyushu Maple</common>
        <altname>Red Snakebark Maple</altname>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer platanoides 'Goldsworth Purple'</latin>
        <common>Norway Maple 'Goldsworth Purple'</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pyrus communis</latin>
        <common>Common Pear</common>
        <altname>European Pear</altname>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Acer pseudoplatanus 'Brilliantissimum'</latin>
        <common>Maple 'Brilliantissimum'</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Chamaecyparis lawsoniana 'Erecta'</latin>
        <common>Lawson's cypress 'Erecta'</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Sorbus x thuringiaca 'Fastigiata'</latin>
        <common>Bastard Service Tree</common>
        <parent>Sorbus aria</parent>
        <parent>Sorbus aucuparia</parent>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus x subhirtella 'Autumnalis Rosea'</latin>
        <common>Rosebud Cherry 'Autumnalis Rosea'</common>
        <parent>Prunus incisa</parent>
        <parent>Prunus spachiana</parent>
        <description>Prunus can be deciduous or evergreen trees or shrubs with showy flowers in spring, and often good autumn foliage colour. Some have edible fruit in autumn, and a few species have ornamental bark. 'Autumnalis Rosea' is a small deciduous tree of spreading habit with ovate leaves turning yellow in autumn, and pale pink, semi-double flowers opening during mild weather from late autumn to early spring.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ulmus x hollandica</latin>
        <common>Dutch Elm</common>
        <parent>Ulmus glabra</parent>
        <parent>Ulmus minor</parent>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Arbutus andrachne</latin>
        <common>Greek strawberry tree</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cercis siliquastrum</latin>
        <common>Judas tree</common>
        <description>This beautiful small deciduous tree can reach a height of 14m. It is a native of south-eastern Europe and western Asia. It was introduced to Britain in 1596 by the herbalist John Gerard.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cotoneaster frigidus</latin>
        <common>Himalayan Tree Cotoneaster</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Crataegus laevigata</latin>
        <common>Midland Hawthorn</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Malus floribunda</latin>
        <common>Japanese crabapple</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Picea</latin>
        <common>Spruce</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pinus mugo</latin>
        <common>Mountain Pine</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus serrula</latin>
        <common>Tibetan cherry</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Salix cinerea</latin>
        <common>Grey Willow</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Tilia x euchlora</latin>
        <common>Crimean Lime</common>
        <parent>Tilia cordata</parent>
        <parent>Tilia dasystyla</parent>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus incisa 'Louisa Lea'</latin>
        <common>Fuji cherry</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Tilia cordata 'Greenspire'</latin>
        <common>Small-leaved lime 'Greenspire'</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus 'Amanogawa'</latin>
        <common>Japanese flowering cherry</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus 'Shirofugen'</latin>
        <common>Japanese flowering cherry</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus 'Tai-haku'</latin>
        <common>Japanese flowering cherry</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus sargentii 'Rancho'</latin>
        <common>Sargent's cherry</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Aesculus indica</latin>
        <common>Indian horse chestnut</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Buddleja davidii</latin>
        <synomym>Buddleia davidii</synomym>
        <common>Buddleia</common>
        <altname>Butterfly Bush</altname>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Laburnum anagyroides</latin>
        <common>Laburnum</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Quercus frainetto</latin>
        <common>Hungarian oak</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ulmus minor 'Atinia'</latin>
        <synomym>Ulmus procera</synomym>
        <common>English elm</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ulmus</latin>
        <common>Elm</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Populus</latin>
        <common>Poplar</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus cerasifera</latin>
        <common>Cherry plum</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Pinus nigra var. nigra</latin>
        <common>Austrian pine</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Alnus</latin>
        <common>Alder</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Aesculus</latin>
        <common>Horse chestnut</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Ilex x altaclerensis</latin>
        <common>Highclere holly</common>
        <parent>Ilex aquifolium</parent>
        <parent>Ilex perado</parent>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Cupressus nootkatensis 'Pendula'</latin>
        <common>Nootka cypress cultivar</common>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Juniperus communis</latin>
        <common>Common Jupiter</common>
        <description>A species of conifer in the genus Juniperus, in the family
            Cupressaceae. A small evergreen coniferous tree or large scrub, common juniper grows to a height of 10m. The berries (really cones) are used to flavour gin.</description>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus x subhirtella</latin>
        <common>Winter flowering cherry</common>
        <altname>Higan Cherry</altname>
    </species>
    <species>
        <latin>Prunus x yedoensis</latin>
        <common>Japanese flowering cherry</common>
        <parent>Prunus speciosa</parent>
        <parent>Prunus pendula f. ascendens</parent>
    </species>
</species-list>
